<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>guidelines on cbrtl</title>
    <link>https://anubhavp.dev/cbrtl//tags/guidelines/</link>
    <description>Recent content in guidelines on cbrtl</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://anubhavp.dev/cbrtl//tags/guidelines/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Showcasing your project on cbrtl</title>
      <link>https://anubhavp.dev/cbrtl//posts/project-showcase/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anubhavp.dev/cbrtl//posts/project-showcase/</guid>
      <description>Some things to keep in mind while adding your project</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This page intends to establish some minor ordinances surrounding project ideas and showcases.
cbrtl was created with the intent of promoting the spirit of Open Source.
Often times, some of the most interesting Open Source projects live in lesser known corners of GitHub,
collecting dust on a lonesome profile with 3-5 followers and an occasionally active commit graph.</p>
<p>Cbrtl is an attempt at stringing together these unrelated projects into a web of resources and dev-logs
that might be of use to on-lookers.</p>
<p>To avoid noisy applications and tutorial cut-pastes, we enforce a standard and a few (lax) rules.</p>
<h1 id="what-constitutes-showcase-worthy-software">What constitutes showcase-worthy software?</h1>
<p>Anything that <strong>serves a clear purpose</strong>.
A project can be showcased if it satisfies the following criteria:</p>
<ul>
<li>Has a proper github <code>README.md</code></li>
<li>Is <strong>not</strong> a tutorial follow-through.
So anything along these lines is generally discouraged:
<ul>
<li>&ldquo;todo app in react&rdquo;</li>
<li>&ldquo;planner app in vue&rdquo;</li>
<li>&ldquo;terminal tic-tac-toe with C&rdquo;</li>
<li>and so on&hellip;</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Is being actively worked on by it&rsquo;s developer(s).
It is <strong>OK</strong> even if it&rsquo;s in infancy when the project is first showcased.</li>
<li>Is open to contribution from people.</li>
<li>Is not a lazy fork (Forks that are some-what different from the parent repos are absolutely okay).</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="examples">Examples</h2>
<p>Here&rsquo;s a few examples to show what we mean by &ldquo;showcase-able projects&rdquo;.
Note that not all of them are from the members of cbrtl, since we&rsquo;re just starting out.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/karnkaul/LittleEngineVk">levk</a>: A 3D Game engine written in C++ and
Vulkan. <strong>Author: <a href="https://github.com/karnkaul">karnage</a></strong></li>
<li><a href="https://aitikgupta.github.io/sociomark/">SocioMark</a>: A social media platform with
plagiarism and attack-proof authenticity checks for user uploaded content.
<strong>Author: <a href="https://github.com/aitikgupta">Aitik Gupta</a></strong></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/srijan-paul/snap">Vyse</a>: A fast, dynamically typed and interpreted programming
language. <strong>Author: <a href="https://github.com/srijan-paul">srijan_</a></strong> (<em>cough</em> self-plug)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/karnkaul/locc">locc</a>: A C++ utility to count lines of code in a project.
<strong>Author: <a href="https://github.com/karnkaul">karnage</a></strong></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/rxi/lume">Lume</a>: A Lua library for gamedev. <strong>Author: <a href="https://github.com/rxi">rxi</a></strong></li>
</ul>
<h1 id="getting-your-project-showcased">Getting your project showcased.</h1>
<p>You have made something, or at least the skeleton of something that will go on to become a full fledged project.
How do you put your code and product on cbrtl?</p>
<ol>
<li>Reach out to us either on the mailing list, or on the discord server.</li>
<li>Have the following ready:
<ul>
<li>A GitHub repo with a well set-up <code>README</code></li>
<li>A (short) write-up describing the scope, aim, tech-stack and architecture
of your project.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Shoot any moderator with the aforementioned and we&rsquo;ll give you:
<ul>
<li>A GitHub repo symlink (<em>symlink?</em>) on the <a href="https://github.com/cbrtl">cbrtl org page</a>.</li>
<li>A community showcase.</li>
<li>A blog post referencing the content from your write-up, describing the project.</li>
<li>Encourage other members to collaborate and contribute.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<p>A good place to start getting involved can be our <a href="https://discord.gg/3qry3u569v">Discord server</a>.</p>
<h1 id="have-an-idea-want-a-team">Have an idea? Want a team?</h1>
<p>It is not so uncommon for programmers to get an idea but not have enough time commitment (or knowledge) to drive the idea to fruition.
If that&rsquo;s how things end up for you, then we might be able to help with pointing you in the right direction.</p>
<p>We may be able to help turn your solo idea into a collaborative work environment.
You can choose to have the repo be on the org, or on your GitHub profile.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
