<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>cbrtl</title>
    <link>https://anubhavp.dev/cbrtl/</link>
    <description>Recent content on cbrtl</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://anubhavp.dev/cbrtl/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Hello world!</title>
      <link>https://anubhavp.dev/cbrtl/posts/what-and-why/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anubhavp.dev/cbrtl/posts/what-and-why/</guid>
      <description>cbrtl - now live</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1 id="what-is-cbrtl">What is cbrtl?</h1>
<p><strong>cbrtl</strong> is an attempt at creating a tight knit group of programmers to showcase and collaborate
on projects and</p>
<h2 id="what-do-we-do-here">What do we do here?</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Create</strong> fun projects. Either in groups or in isolation.</li>
<li>Organize community and online <strong>showcases</strong> for group and individual projects.</li>
<li><strong>Contribute</strong> to Open Source projects both in cbrtl and in other communities.</li>
<li>Conduct <strong>code reviews</strong> and <strong>JAM</strong>s.</li>
<li>Share <strong>resources</strong> to learn.</li>
<li>Create and maintain <strong>dev-journals and blogs</strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="what-is-the-end-goal">What is the end goal?</h2>
<p>Merely to promote Open Source culture and proper software development within our college.</p>
<h2 id="how-far-down-the-road-are-we">How far down the road are we?</h2>
<p>Not that far, the egg has just been laid.
As of the time of writing this post, we have just started out.
For the effort to work out, we welcome interested folks over :)</p>
<h2 id="what-can-i-do">What can I do?</h2>
<p>Just what you&rsquo;ve been doing so far, but with more people!</p>
<p>If you have any interesting projects that you have already been working on,
let us know and we&rsquo;ll put them on the cbrtl page for more people to see.
Note that there is some criteria that projects must qualify, some of these are intentionally vague.
But as long as you&rsquo;re doing more than following a course or tutorial, it&rsquo;s likely to be accepted :)</p>
<h1 id="volunteering-to-cbrtl">Volunteering to cbrtl</h1>
<p>We are looking for volunteers for some roles.
Note however, that there is no strict mandate for responsibilities.
As long as you&rsquo;re capable of adding <em>something</em> of value, no matter how small, shoot us a message!
We&rsquo;re looking for some help with:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Code reviewers</strong>: If you have experience contributing to FOSS or writing code for user/developer
facing products, perhaps you can volunteer and help us out here :)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Editors</strong>: We plan on writing frequent blog posts.
But both the technical content and the english material can use a second pair of eyes to help catch mistakes or inconsistent writing.
If you have done some technical writing before, you can volunteer for reviewing the content in blog posts!</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Technical Writers</strong>: If you have experience writing code but are usually on a tight schedule, you
may be able to join us and share your knowledge. We want to mandate a high quality in our posts, so any
tutorial/how-to guide that has been done a million times before is generally discouraged. We want
to avoid redundant topics like &ldquo;How to build a todo app with React&rdquo; and promote posts and dev-logs /
journals that are fun to read and explore.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Frontend devs</strong>: Currently, the cbrtl website is bland and not-so-catchy.
While minimalism is the core idea, we can definitely use some front-end developers to help keep the UI fresh, responsive and modern.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Moderators</strong>: To help keep the community together on discord and github.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>NOTE</strong> We do not expect any amount of time commitment from volunteers, as long as you can make small
contributions, we appreciate it.
Volunteering is not druge work, and active frequent contributions are appreciated, but not required.</p>
<h1 id="the-kind-of-software-we-want-to-write">The kind of software we want to write</h1>
<p>We firmly believe in re-inventing the wheel.
Writing software close to the metal helps us closely understand the behind-the-scenes of software that most take for granted.
While any creative project is welcome, here are some ideas that adhere to the spirit:</p>
<ul>
<li>Compilers</li>
<li>Virtual Machines and Interpreters</li>
<li>Game Engines</li>
<li>Operating Systems</li>
<li>Search Engines</li>
<li>Database engines</li>
<li>Voxel renderers</li>
<li>TCP/IP stack</li>
<li>VCS</li>
</ul>
<p>All of these are but regular software that we tend to take for granted, that can be (and have been) written from scratch.
We encourage all kinds of creative projects no matter how basic.
But you can expect the above group projects to come to life as the community grows.</p>
<h2 id="showcasing-your-project">Showcasing your project</h2>
<p><a href="https://anubhavp.dev/cbrtl//posts/project-showcase/">This</a> post has more on that.
If you want to showcase your project on our github org, then reach out to us on discord or the mailing list.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Zuzu</title>
      <link>https://anubhavp.dev/cbrtl/posts/zuzu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anubhavp.dev/cbrtl/posts/zuzu/</guid>
      <description>Zuzu is a static site generator that converts all your markdown files into static htmls pages. It uses Github falvoured Markdown CSS and highlight js to beautify code snippets.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1 id="zuzu">Zuzu</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>Static Site Generator</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="zuzu-is-a-minimal-static-site-generator">Zuzu is a minimal static site generator</h3>
<p>Zuzu converts all your markdown files into static htmls pages to be rendered quickly. It uses Github falvoured Markdown CSS and highlight js to beautify code snippets. <a href="https://anubhavp.me/blog">This blog</a>, for example, has been written using this generator. This enables noobs like me to write blogs without having to learn a lot of code! All you need to do is to write a markdown file and it will be rendered as a page ;)</p>
<h2 id="how-does-it-work-">How does it work ?</h2>
<p>Zuzu parses the markdown file using <em>javascript</em> and renders it as <em>html documents</em>. It then saves the html files in the <code>public</code> folder. The public folder, with <code>index.html</code> file, is the final output of the generator and this can be deployed and hosted in various platforms. This particular blog has been deployed on <a href="https://anubhavp.me/blog/">Github Pages</a>.</p>
<h3 id="1-create-a-markdown-file">1. Create a markdown file</h3>
<pre><code># This is a title
This is a paragraph
This is another paragraph
This is a list:
* Item 1
* Item 2
* Item 3
This is a code block:
```
print(&quot;Hello World&quot;)
```
This is a table:
| Column 1 | Column 2 | Column 3 |
| -------- | -------- | -------- |
| 1        | 2        | 3        |
| 4        | 5        | 6        |
| 7        | 8        | 9        |
This is a link: [zuzu](https://anubhavp.me/blog/zuzu.html)
</code></pre>
<h3 id="2-run-the-generator-and-find-your-blog">2. Run the generator and find your blog</h3>
<p>Run <code>npm run generate</code> in the console. Zuzu is also available as a CLI tool. You can install it using <code>npm install -g zuzu</code>. Then run <code>npx zuzussg</code> in the console. This will generate the html files in the <code>public</code> folder. You can then deploy the <code>public</code> folder to any hosting platform.
You&rsquo;ll now see the blog in the public folder! Run the index.html file in your browser to see your blog. You may now deploy your site
to a server. Zuzu also supports CI/CD. You can use Github Actions to automatically deploy your site to Github Pages.</p>
<h3 id="you-can-find-the-working-in-the-repo-herehttpsgithubcomcodebotxzuzu">You can find the working in the repo <a href="https://github.com/codebotx/zuzu/">here</a></h3>
<h4 id="to-do">To-do</h4>
<ul>
<li>Add another template file in the initial folder with index.html and respective assets.</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Vyse</title>
      <link>https://anubhavp.dev/cbrtl/posts/vyse/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anubhavp.dev/cbrtl/posts/vyse/</guid>
      <description>A dynamically typed, interpreted and fast scriptling language inspired by Lua for rapid prototyping of applications like video games.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sometime during my 2nd year in college, I&rsquo;d made a hobby programming language that turned out quite well.
It&rsquo;s named &ldquo;Vyse&rdquo;, after <a href="https://dota2.fandom.com/wiki/Scythe_of_Vyse">Guinsoo&rsquo;s Scythe of Vyse</a> from DotA.</p>
<p>Vyse is a dynamically typed, interpreted and fast scriptling language inspired by Lua for rapid prototyping of applications like video games.
Programmers familiar with Lua/Javascript can pick up the language within an hour.
Vyse also comes with a C++ API for frictionless embedding in projects.</p>
<p>Features include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Modules, both native and user-level</li>
<li>An embedding API</li>
<li>Closures, higher order functions to facilitate FP.</li>
<li>Prototypical inheritance, inspired from JS and Lua.</li>
</ul>
<p>Since the language already has detailed (but remarkably outdated) documentation on <a href="https://injuly.in/vyse">its website</a>,
I won&rsquo;t bother rewriting any of that here.</p>
<p>Instead, here is the simple number-guessing program:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#fff;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-rs" data-lang="rs"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="font-weight:bold">const</span> math = import(<span style="font-style:italic">&#34;math&#34;</span>)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="font-weight:bold">fn</span> play() {
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="font-weight:bold">const</span> num = math.randint(0, 100)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="font-weight:bold">let</span> guess = input(<span style="font-style:italic">&#34;guess: &#34;</span>):<span style="font-weight:bold">to_num</span>()
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="font-weight:bold">let</span> n_attempts = 1
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="font-weight:bold">while</span> guess != num {
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    <span style="font-weight:bold">if</span> guess &lt; num {
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      print(<span style="font-style:italic">&#34;Too low! Try higher.&#34;</span>)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    } <span style="font-weight:bold">else</span> {
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      print(<span style="font-style:italic">&#34;Too high! Try lower.&#34;</span>)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    }
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    n_attempts += 1
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    guess = input(<span style="font-style:italic">&#34;guess: &#34;</span>):<span style="font-weight:bold">to_num</span>()
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  }
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  print(<span style="font-style:italic">&#34;Well done! number of attempts: &#34;</span>, n_attempts)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>}
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>play()
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Of course, it&rsquo;s possible to do more than just write simple terminal programs.
For instance, I&rsquo;m currently working on a <a href="https://github.com/cpp-gamedev/wex">2D game engine</a>
that will allow users to write games with the language.
This project hasn&rsquo;t seen any major progress in the past year owing to my busy (read: poorly managed) schedule,
however, I&rsquo;m looking to resume this project in the coming quarter.</p>
<p>Currently, there are no official releases for Vyse.
This is majorly due to me not being in possession of a windows (yuck) device ATM.
There are some bugs that I&rsquo;ve yet to prune out before I can make a stable v0.1 release for all platforms.</p>
<p>The one benefit of having no users, is a leisurely development pace.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FAQ</title>
      <link>https://anubhavp.dev/cbrtl/posts/faq/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anubhavp.dev/cbrtl/posts/faq/</guid>
      <description>Before you ask...</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="why-is-it-called-cbrtl">Why is it called &lsquo;cbrtl&rsquo;?</h2>
<p><del>Because every other GitHub org name was taken</del>.</p>
<p>It comes from the C stdlib function <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/cpp/c-runtime-library/reference/cbrt-cbrtf-cbrtl?view=msvc-160">cbrtl</a>.</p>
<p>There is a some trivia to the oddly text-to-speechified name.</p>
<p>In older versions of ANSI C, only the first 6 characters of an identifier were considered when compiling source code.
So most standard library functions in C have odd names like <code>strstr</code>, <code>strtod</code>, <code>alloca</code> and so on&hellip;</p>
<h2 id="why-at-all">Why at all?</h2>
<p>Some of my acquaintances from other colleges have clubs, groups and spaces dedicated to open source and software
development. Couple of days ago, I came across IIT Roorkee&rsquo;s <a href="https://sdslabs.co/">SDSLabs </a> and PES Uni&rsquo;s <a href="https://pesos.github.io/">PES Open Source</a>.  After looking into it
a bit more, turns out most colleges these days have their own groups for related stuff.</p>
<p>We thought it would be fun to have a similar group of like minded developers from our college.</p>
<p>Is it too ambitious? We won&rsquo;t know until we don&rsquo;t try.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-it-that-cbrtl-aims-to-do-exactly">What is it that cbrtl aims to do exactly?</h2>
<p>Good question.
We don&rsquo;t have a concrete answer.
That said, I&rsquo;ll throw in most of what we&rsquo;ve gathered from our goal so far, and you decide if you like the sound of it.</p>
<ul>
<li>Contributing to Open Source.</li>
<li>Talks and meetups.</li>
<li>Showcasing projects from individuals and teams.</li>
<li>Code reviews and educational blogs (hopefully ones that haven&rsquo;t been done to death before&hellip;).</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="what-platforms-are-you-present-on">What platforms are you present on?</h2>
<p>For now, our presence is limited to <a href="">Discord</a> and the <a href="https://github.com/cbrtl">GitHub organization</a>.
Mostly because these are very solid platforms and we are tight on the number of people moderating.</p>
<h2 id="what-skills-do-i-need">What skills do I need?</h2>
<p>Not much.</p>
<ul>
<li>The ability to code.</li>
<li>The willingness to learn.</li>
<li>Basic knowledge of Git and GitHub.</li>
</ul>
<p>Even 1 and 3 are optional.</p>
<h2 id="where-do-i-join">Where do I join?</h2>
<p>As mentioned earlier,  you can join the <a href="">Discord</a> and the <a href="https://github.com/cbrtl">GitHub organization</a>.
More info on <a href="/">Getting started with cbrtl and Open Source</a>.</p>
<h2 id="is-there-anything-i-can-do-to-help">Is there anything I can do to help?</h2>
<p>You can volunteer to help us keep the community thriving.
We are looking for volunteers who can help with:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Front end development</strong>: To touch up the current blog site.</li>
<li><strong>Moderation</strong>: To manage the discord server and the GitHub org.</li>
<li><strong>Code reviews</strong>: To mandate some code quality for those who demand it.</li>
<li><strong>Technical Writers</strong>: To aid in writing blog posts.</li>
<li><strong>Editors</strong>: A second pair of eyes helps catch common mistakes in writing :)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="is-this-an-official-college-club">Is this an official college club?</h2>
<p>No.
This is an entirely independent student initiative that is looking for active participation.
A decentralized group of like-minded programmers.</p>
<h2 id="will-there-be-events-with-cash-prizes">Will there be events with cash prizes?</h2>
<p>No.
And we want to be upfront about it.
We want to keep this community closed to people who code because they like creating.
Of course, that is not to say we discredit any other motivation you may have.</p>
<p>As such, we won&rsquo;t conduct any competitions with cash prizes for the foreseeable future.
Other clubs (which are official) in our college do a great (<del>citation needed*</del>) job at that regardless.</p>
<h2 id="what-kinds-of-events-can-i-expect">What kinds of events can I expect?</h2>
<p>Other than project showcases and on-demand code review sessions, we are open to other ideas.</p>
<p>Not as much of an &rsquo;event&rsquo; but you can expect group projects that will (hopefully) be active throughout.</p>
<h2 id="i-have-some-other-questions-where-can-i-ask">I have some other questions, where can I ask?</h2>
<p>You&rsquo;re more than welcome on the mailing list, or in the discord server.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Showcasing your project on cbrtl</title>
      <link>https://anubhavp.dev/cbrtl/posts/project-showcase/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anubhavp.dev/cbrtl/posts/project-showcase/</guid>
      <description>Some things to keep in mind while adding your project</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This page intends to establish some minor ordinances surrounding project ideas and showcases.
cbrtl was created with the intent of promoting the spirit of Open Source.
Often times, some of the most interesting Open Source projects live in lesser known corners of GitHub,
collecting dust on a lonesome profile with 3-5 followers and an occasionally active commit graph.</p>
<p>Cbrtl is an attempt at stringing together these unrelated projects into a web of resources and dev-logs
that might be of use to on-lookers.</p>
<p>To avoid noisy applications and tutorial cut-pastes, we enforce a standard and a few (lax) rules.</p>
<h1 id="what-constitutes-showcase-worthy-software">What constitutes showcase-worthy software?</h1>
<p>Anything that <strong>serves a clear purpose</strong>.
A project can be showcased if it satisfies the following criteria:</p>
<ul>
<li>Has a proper github <code>README.md</code></li>
<li>Is <strong>not</strong> a tutorial follow-through.
So anything along these lines is generally discouraged:
<ul>
<li>&ldquo;todo app in react&rdquo;</li>
<li>&ldquo;planner app in vue&rdquo;</li>
<li>&ldquo;terminal tic-tac-toe with C&rdquo;</li>
<li>and so on&hellip;</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Is being actively worked on by it&rsquo;s developer(s).
It is <strong>OK</strong> even if it&rsquo;s in infancy when the project is first showcased.</li>
<li>Is open to contribution from people.</li>
<li>Is not a lazy fork (Forks that are some-what different from the parent repos are absolutely okay).</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="examples">Examples</h2>
<p>Here&rsquo;s a few examples to show what we mean by &ldquo;showcase-able projects&rdquo;.
Note that not all of them are from the members of cbrtl, since we&rsquo;re just starting out.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/karnkaul/LittleEngineVk">levk</a>: A 3D Game engine written in C++ and
Vulkan. <strong>Author: <a href="https://github.com/karnkaul">karnage</a></strong></li>
<li><a href="https://aitikgupta.github.io/sociomark/">SocioMark</a>: A social media platform with
plagiarism and attack-proof authenticity checks for user uploaded content.
<strong>Author: <a href="https://github.com/aitikgupta">Aitik Gupta</a></strong></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/srijan-paul/snap">Vyse</a>: A fast, dynamically typed and interpreted programming
language. <strong>Author: <a href="https://github.com/srijan-paul">srijan_</a></strong> (<em>cough</em> self-plug)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/karnkaul/locc">locc</a>: A C++ utility to count lines of code in a project.
<strong>Author: <a href="https://github.com/karnkaul">karnage</a></strong></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/rxi/lume">Lume</a>: A Lua library for gamedev. <strong>Author: <a href="https://github.com/rxi">rxi</a></strong></li>
</ul>
<h1 id="getting-your-project-showcased">Getting your project showcased.</h1>
<p>You have made something, or at least the skeleton of something that will go on to become a full fledged project.
How do you put your code and product on cbrtl?</p>
<ol>
<li>Reach out to us either on the mailing list, or on the discord server.</li>
<li>Have the following ready:
<ul>
<li>A GitHub repo with a well set-up <code>README</code></li>
<li>A (short) write-up describing the scope, aim, tech-stack and architecture
of your project.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Shoot any moderator with the aforementioned and we&rsquo;ll give you:
<ul>
<li>A GitHub repo symlink (<em>symlink?</em>) on the <a href="https://github.com/cbrtl">cbrtl org page</a>.</li>
<li>A community showcase.</li>
<li>A blog post referencing the content from your write-up, describing the project.</li>
<li>Encourage other members to collaborate and contribute.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<p>A good place to start getting involved can be our <a href="https://discord.gg/3qry3u569v">Discord server</a>.</p>
<h1 id="have-an-idea-want-a-team">Have an idea? Want a team?</h1>
<p>It is not so uncommon for programmers to get an idea but not have enough time commitment (or knowledge) to drive the idea to fruition.
If that&rsquo;s how things end up for you, then we might be able to help with pointing you in the right direction.</p>
<p>We may be able to help turn your solo idea into a collaborative work environment.
You can choose to have the repo be on the org, or on your GitHub profile.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting started with cbrtl and FOSS</title>
      <link>https://anubhavp.dev/cbrtl/posts/getting-started/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://anubhavp.dev/cbrtl/posts/getting-started/</guid>
      <description>Grinding gears</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>So you read up on open source, read up on <a href="https://anubhavp.dev/cbrtl//posts/what-and-why/">cbrtl</a> and want to start hacking.
There are some preliminaries that you should take care of first.
These are listed in order:</p>
<ol>
<li>Create a GitHub account.</li>
<li>Set up git on your local computer.
<ul>
<li>If you&rsquo;re on windows, download <a href="https://git-scm.com/downloads">GitBash</a> and follow the install instructions.</li>
<li>Get a personal test repo set up and try out commands like <code>push</code>, <code>commit</code>, <code>pull</code> etc.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Join the <a href="https://github.com/cbrtl">GitHub organization</a> by adding yourself to the members list (More on that below).</li>
<li>Join the <a href="">Discord server</a>.</li>
</ol>
<p>Alright, you&rsquo;re set to start out.
At this point, I would recommend getting familiar with GitHub, reading up some articles and blogs.
I highly recommend <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/git/tutorials">Atlassian&rsquo;s git tutorials</a> and documentation.</p>
<h1 id="making-your-first-pull-request">Making your first Pull Request</h1>
<p>(<strong>NOTE:</strong> If you have experience using git and don&rsquo;t want to waste time, just ping the <code>@cbrtl moderator</code> role on discord and we&rsquo;ll add you).</p>
<p>If you had to follow through the above, then it&rsquo;s likely that you&rsquo;ve never made a PR before.
To get your feet wet, make your first PR on our <a href="https://github.com/cbrtl/members-list">member&rsquo;s list repo</a>.
Once you do that, you&rsquo;ll be recognized as a member of cbrtl on GitHub.
You will find a step by step guide on how to do that on the repository&rsquo;s <code>README</code>.</p>
<p>Done? Great! 🎉</p>
<p>Now you&rsquo;re going to have to wait for a moderator to merge your PR.
That should be done by the time you&rsquo;re done reading this article ;)</p>
<h1 id="getting-the-most-out-of-it">Getting the most out of it</h1>
<p>The way you grow and shape your journey into Open Source is dictated by your level of engagement with people, and participation
in projects, discussions and the like.
Now then, how do you define &ldquo;engagement&rdquo; and &ldquo;participation&rdquo;?
It can mean different things for different people, but the recurring ideas are the same.</p>
<h2 id="ways-to-participate">Ways to participate</h2>
<ul>
<li>Contributing to the <a href="https://github.com/cbrtl/cbrtl-site">blog</a>.</li>
<li>Part-taking in open source projects being built in the community.</li>
<li>Coming up with your own project ideas, and getting people to contribute.</li>
<li>Showcasing projects you have made on cbrtl blog and GitHub organization.</li>
<li>Contributing to larger open source projects outside cbrtl.</li>
<li>Asking questions, getting to know people better.</li>
<li>Volunteering on development and content moderation. <a href="http://anubhavp.dev/cbrtl//posts/what-and-why/#volunteering-to-cbrtl">Details here</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="starting-your-own-project">Starting your own project.</h2>
<p>It would be great to have more interesting projects available for people to work on.
Look at the <a href="http://anubhavp.dev/cbrtl//posts/project-showcase/">project showcase post</a> for relevant information.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
